<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-building-titanic</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85042462/1908-04-23/ed-1/seq-1/#words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>WHITE STAR LINE TO BUILD
BIGGEST SHIPS YET PROJECTED
By Associated Press.
LIVERPOOL. April Two new
White Star liners which will be the
largest vessels yet projected will be
laid down at Belfast next June. The
exact measurements of the steamers
have not been given out/but they will
be over 840 feet In length, 78 feet in
breadth and with a gross tonnage of
45,000, or 50,000.
The ships are to be fitted with com
bination turbines and reciprocating
engines guaranteed to maintain a
speed of twenty-one knots. The names
of the vessels are to be Olympic and
Titanic. '.'./.-</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026749/1908-10-02/ed-1/seq-9/#words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>MAMMOTH LINERS LINERSPUZZLE LINERSPUZZLEOFFICIALS
PUZZLE PUZZLEOFFICIALS PUZZLEOFFICIALSEnglishmen OFFICIALS OFFICIALSEnglishmen
Englishmen Fear 60000Ton 60000TonBoats 60OOOTonBoats 60f000TonBoats
Boats Cant Be BeDocked BeDocked BeDocked
Docked DockedLONDON DockedLONDON DockedLONDON
LONDON Oct 2 2Brltl British h shipbuilding shipbuildingexperts ebipbulkllngexperts shipbuildingexperts
experts are puzzled to know how the theWhite theWhite theWhite
White Star officiate will land passen passengers p paseengem s en engers ¬
gers and cargo fromuthe tront fro tbe a lines two pro prospective protpectie propective ¬
spective 80000 tonn tonnars the Titanic and andOlympic andhmpfc andt
Olympic OlympicThe t ilympicThe hmpfcThe
The Mauretanla and Lusitania of not notmuch notmuch notmuch
much more than half ha1 the proposed proposedcrafts propo proposedcrafts ed edrafts
crafts tonnage have no more room roomthan roomtllan roomthan
than they need to get through the theAmbrose theAmbroee theAmbrose
Ambrose channel and Into the Mersey Merseynt
nt tt t Liverpool LiverpoolThe LiverpoolThe LiverpoolThe
The popular opinion here Is that a avessel afssel avessel
vessel of 0600 tons would have to todo tod tolo
do d Its loading and unloading at sea seaMarine 3eLlarlne seaMarine
Marine statisticians stati tJdans have figured that thatthe thattite
I
the t he tonnage of the e entire Spanish ar arnada armada armada
mada of 129 l ships ships which tried to land landan landn
an n army In England in Queen Eliza Elizabeths EJlzahetbs Elizabeths ¬
beths reign was only 50139 50139Considerable 58139Considerable 13 13Considerable
Considerable progress is being made madewith madewith madewith
with construction work on the Olym Olympic Olympic Olympie ¬
pic In Harland Wolffs yard at atBelfast atBElrut atBelfast
Belfast but the Titanic keel blocks blockswill blockswill l lwill
will not be laid until January JanuaryFIREMEN JanuaryFIREMEN i</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1909-01-03/ed-1/seq-59/#words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>A MIGHTY CRADLE FOR GIGANTIC TWINS.
This aantry cost $\COO,COO. It was erected fop the express purooie of corstructinn the two new
White Star steamships, Olympic and Titanic.

ONE MILLION FOR A STARTER
After an expenditure of J1.C00.000 the great stee!
j double gantry which will bo the cradle of th» larg
! est two steamship In the world ha« been finished
I at the shipyards of Harland  "WoifT. at Belfast.
Ireland. The steamers whose keel blocks haT»
I been laid side by side in this the biggest gantry
j In the world are the Titanic and th« Olympic, of
| the White Star Line, and within a year or two
I these leviathans will b« running between New Tori*
! and Southampton.
Soon after the two fast Cunarders. too Lusl-
I taria and the Mauretania, had demonstrated that
I one could travel in luxury and at a very high
i speed through tha agency of turbine engines. th«
White Star X-in» announced that it would build
two steamers to beat the Oinarders la length and
breadth, and perhaps In other ways also. It was
reported at the tim» that th« new Whlta Star
■ liners would be a thousand feet in length, but sub
sequently it was officially announced that they
i would bo 900 feet lons, with a beam of ninety feet.
j When It was decided to build them it was found
' that there was no gantry In thm world big enough
! to accommodate such monsters, and It was then
. that Hrland  Wolff began to rip up three of Its
', largest gantries and build the hug* steel and con
' crete cradle that Is now ready to bold th* Olympic
• and the Titanic.
Before th* steel structure which supports th*
i powerful electric travailing cranes was erected a
' big concrete base, twenty fret thick, was built upon
sp!le3 driven fifty fe«t into tha ground. The con
crete foundation, in addition to being more firm
than the regular earthen base, has the advantage
of cleanliness, an 1 tools and materials which mar
fall from the cranes la the course of construction
may be found more readily. Parts of deck fittings
end tools have fallen into the ground la gantries
with earth bases and have not been recovered
' until the vessel has gilded from Its cradle into the
: water.
The construction of the Olympic has been started.
' The keel of the Titanic will be laid soon, and
' visitors to the shipyards at Belfast will have an
opportunity of seeing the simultaneous csnstrcs
. tion. side by side, of the largest two steamers tn
; the world. The gantries are so built that any
piece of material, however heavy or awkward, may
[ be placed and held In whatever position the con
atructora desire. The gantries themselves are more
than a thousand feet in length. 3C3 feet high and
something more than two hundred feet</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1909-05-30/ed-1/seq-59/#words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>TWO XEW GIAXTS OF SEA.
The Titanic and the Olympic W3l
lie Largest Steamships in World.
Although what will be the largest two steamships
In the world, the Titanic and the Olympic, of the
White Star Line, are mere skeletons just now in
their Lie million-dollar double gantry at Belfast,
Ireland the marine architects know exactly bow
they are going to look when they start on their
maiden passage to this port. From the plans and
specifications the designers have made a wush
drawing showing bow 'he monsters will look when
In the water and ready to sail. Although at nrst
glance the illustration suggests the Isauretania and
Lusitania. with their four gigantic funnels, there
Is something in the appearance of the new levia
thans that Is typical of a White Star steamship.
The great height of the new liners and the broad
sweep of the bridge elves some idea of their 80.J80
tons displacement. The builders have almost elimi
nated the old cusr im of carying masts, «nd In this
respect the targesi ships in the world resemble the
Old Dominion steamers, tha smallest passenger
carrying vessels in the American coastwise service.
All the old Dominior Mners have only one mast.
■ • . g the 1 ■ '
;i' i Titanic.
Thrse tw vessels are being built simultaneously
sid* by side In a steel gantry that was begun a
year before the keels were laid, and which cost
over a million dollars. The new liners will each
n«» S» feet long, with ■ 92-foot beam. The unusual
beam la equivalent to the length of some of the
fast utenrn yachts of this port. The Olympic and
Titanic will iw» read] for the New York. South
ampton an.i Cherbourg *»*r\ im of the White Star
IJne in 1911. The builders are Harland a Wolff.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn93063916/1910-01-08/ed-1/seq-1/#words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE WORLDS LARGEST VESSEL VESSELTHE VESSELTHE ESSEIJTHE
THE TITANIC NOW NO BEING BUILT
Here la an architectural picture of the steamship Titanic which Is being beingbuilt beingbunt beingbuilt
built for the White Star line at Belfast also a view of the giant steel cradle cradleiu
iu which the ship Is being constructed The keel of the steamship Is seen in inthe inthe inthe
the lower photograph The White Star company Is to have two of these theselaviathans theselebtthans theseleviathans
leviathans and they will be In commission early in 1911 Their launching launchingwill
will UI signalize a most important era in marine achievement for they will be bobyc beby beby
byc byctil by all odds the largest vessels in the world The Titanic and Olympic will willench wUlh willeach
each h be SCO feet f t in length 92 feet beam 45000 tons register and GOOOO tons tonsdisplacement tonsdl tonsdlstixccnwnt
displacement dl Ilem nt These enormous dimensions are best expressed In comparl comparlS
30115 S The Washington Va hlngton monument is r x55 55 5 feet high and the Metropolitan tower towerlit
lit New Xt York rliy r f ity rises TOO feet Tbe combined tonnage tonnn e of tbe Olympic Olympicand OIrJ11pllukl <
and Tlrxink k far fn r exceeds the tonnage ton n e of all It II the vrbs vessels tssl els ls engaged pn n ngld tM1 on both bothskies bothkles bothskies
skies In the hlsi hI Irlt + rl conflict of the Spanish armada HfuJ dn Hud nd It Is even more In Interesting Inttresrln inttirestinx ¬
teresting to know ihir t t the Santa Maria was only em I rIt ii 0 feet fi Plat i t Ions IOll a and d 233 tons tonsvet tonhtnhn tonelnirien
htnhn t vet tat nn thl visw yf f 4r1 1 Columbus Journeyed TO th thp new UP world</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045433/1910-01-23/ed-1/seq-14//#words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
SHIPS TO BE LARGEST LARGESTVessels LARGESTV LARGESTVessels
Vessels V e sels Under Construction Constructionin
in Belfast l e1fast to Surpass All AllFOE AllFOR AllFOR
FOR TRANSATLANTIC SERVICE SEEVICEOlympic SERVICEOlnplc SERVICEOlympic
Olympic and Titanic Will Have Ton Tonnnsre TGDnn Tonnnge
nnsre nn e Twice as Great an the Maure Maureiania Mauretania Iaureinnln
tania and Lnnitanla and Former FormerWill FormerWill
Will 111 He Ready Rend for Launching In InAnjfimt InAngulltOther inAugustOther
Anjfimt AngulltOther Other Year Later LaterLondon LaterLondon LaterLondon
London Jan 22Whl1e 22 While the navy 1Ml departments de departments deJHlrtments ¬
partments of various governments are aretrying aretrying aretrying
trying to outdo each eachot other In the building buildingof
of mammoth battle ships the transAt transAtlantic transAtlanUc transAtlantic ¬
lantic companies are not IdltS IdltSGreat Idl IdlGreat idit iditGreat
Great strides are being made at Harland Har Harland Harland
land Wolffs shipyards in Belfast in intKe InUie intire
tire construction of the two White Star Starleviathans Starleviathans Starleviathans
leviathans Olympic and Titanic which whichare whichare whichare
are to surpass in tonnage and size the theMauretania therauretanla titeMauretania
Mauretania and her sister ship the Lust Lusitania Lusltanla Lusttania
tania taniaThe tanlaThe taniaThe
The Olympic will be ready for launch launching launching launching
ing In August and the Titanic at the end endof endof endof
of next year eftr The following are the thedimensions thedimensions thedimensions
dimensions of each vessel compared with withother withother
other gigantic liners
Length LengthTonmzB Le1IgtllTG9Me LeiiethTonsaa
TonmzB in feet feetOtjMpie feetObpic feetotnaic
OtjMpie 6000 601 + 18 HO 140narie 0 0TUufe
TUufe 11 6009 SO SO1MInICaI 110alurecsak 40 40MmtroUwbi
MmtroUwbi 1MInICaI a 31933 n9J ltd ltdLsMtaela TECLmtaMfe 7eeLMta
LmtaMfe LMta v 31I60 7C 7CAdriatic 7S 7Se TicAdriatic
Adriatic e 4J5U I 1511 l J09 J09Iteitie i iBut 709liskie
Iteitie c 236 m mBut 8 8But
But it is in the appointments of the new newvessels newvessels
vessels v els that the greatest interest centers centersThey centersThey
They are not to be built for speed but butJfor buttor butfor
for the comfort and convenience of passengers pas passengers p5seng ¬
sengers seng sengers rs
sengersFive
Five Thousand Passenger PassengerThere IasscngersThere
There will bee greater deck and cabin cabinspace cabinspace cabinspace
space Each ship will be able to carry carry5k
5000 persons and the crew of each will willnumber willnumber 111 111number
number 600 600The 600The O0The
The ships will be floating hotels hotelsThey hotelsThe hotelsThey
They The are the first liners to afford their theirpatrons theirpatrons theirpetronsthe
patrons petronsthe the luxuries of a a swimming bath bathsufficiently bathsufficiently bathsufficiently
sufficiently deep to permit of diving divingCabins divingCabins divingCabins
Cabins aro to be constructed with private privateshower privateshower privateshower
shower and slipper baths bathsA bathsA bathsA
A commodious and wellappointed gym gymnasium gmna gymnasium ¬
nasium na tum is to give voyagers an opportu opportunity opportunity opportunity ¬
nity for daily exercise while spacious spaciousplayrooms spacIousplrooms spaciousplayrooms
playrooms decorated with panels repre representing representing represeating ¬
senting fairy fa I rJ tales and popular fables fableswill fableswill fableswill
will be provided for the children childrenDrawingrooms chUdronDrawlngrooms childrenDrawingrooms
Drawingrooms smokingrooms and a alibrary 2 2lIbrnry alibrary
library are to be at the disposal of the thevoyagers theotagers thevoyagers
voyagers One of the decks will be de devoted devoted devoted ¬
voted to an extensive ballroom and andaltould andIIhould andshould
should the fashion prevail a large skat skatIng skatIng skating
Ing rink will tys provided providedIn
In a sentence passengers may skate skatedance skatedance skatedance
dance smoke swim and dive and prac practice prnctice practice ¬
tice the arts of physical culture at their theirwill theirwill theirwill
will willThere
There are of course to be many din diningrooms dInIngrooms diningrooms ¬
ingrooms The principal one which is isto Isto isto
to be elaborately decorated will seat no nofewer nofewer nofewer
fewer than 800 00 This is to be the most mostcommodious mostcommodious mostcommodious
commodious apartment on the ship shipCOMING shipCOMING shipCOMING</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045555/1910-02-04/ed-1/seq-3/#words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>MONSTER LINERS
New TransAtlantic Boats to Carry
Five Thousand Persons
WELVE thousand tons rep
resents the Increase In size
of the two mammoth liners
Olympic and Titanic nOW
being built by Messr9 Harlllnd Wolff
Belfast for the White Star company
over the leviathan Cunarders Mauro
tanla and Lusltanla The tonnage or
each of these Is 33000 tons that of
each or the new White Star boats
13 to bo 45000 tons and possibly
more Among the Belfast shipyard
workmen these great vessels have been
known for months past as the mystery
ships because ot the extraordinary
precautions which have been taken
to prevent their dimensions and de
sign becoming public property Some
thing however may now be said on
theso points
The new steamers will be complet
ed about the end of next year and
will go on the Southampton1eW York
service In the following spring They
will be by far the largest In the world
o
ONE MORE DAY OF
I i HALF PRICE SUITS
If you buy your suit to
t ctn F k > morrow you save just half
900 to 2000according to
the price you pay A big lot of I
s i y x t F these Sots left Many Benja I
k n z mill Suits
L Regular 1800 to 4000
Now at 900 to 2000
This Item to Mothers
3 y Ve have a splendid line of
hpo boys knee pants included in
the sale tomorrow 50c and
85c values for 25c 100
values for 50c
and 150
t3MJamllCloth e
knee styles only
Jlfn4 6 nJaln e uraa Straight
I p l e
I
J D OWE Manager 245 Main Street
I
r
t
H
und In equipment and decoration will
bo the finest on the water The new
vessels will have A displacement or
GOOOO tons They are to bo about
910 feet long with 0 beam or 90
feet and tho boat deck will bo mora
than 60 feet above the water
Neither the Olympic nor the Titanic
will bo highpower boats nor are their
lines designed for great speed 21 knots
being the average almod at as
against the 25 of the Cunnrdors All
immense amount of space which III
fast boats IG devoted to machinery
will thus be saved for cabin accomm
dation The carryIng capacity or the
great boats will exceed that of any
al1olt today by Ilt least onethlrl1
Each steamship will carry under nor
mal condition moro than jOOO per
sons all told
The crow will bo the largest ever
employed on one merchant ship
more than GOO In all The monster
now liner will have nine steel decks
The steamers arc not only designed
to eclipse everything else as yet
achIeved In passenger shipbuilding nq
regards the size but In their novelty
of equipment as well There will be a
large entrance hall a spacious din
ng room smolelngroom library
wornens parlor grill and lounging
rooms elaborately furnished to the
last detail
One of the upper decks III to he
completely Inclosel1 to serve as a ball
room or skating rInk By day this In
closure mar be used ns a sun parlor
anti promenade It will he largo
enough to accommodate several hun
dred passengers In planning the I
cabins of the new liners the luxuries
of the most uptodllte hotels have I
been kept in sight and even Improv I
ed upon These boats will offer not
only extended suites of room but
complete flats which will mako It
possible to cross the Atlantic while
enjoYing all the privacy or ones own
homo
The Olympic and Titanic will ho the
first steamers to offer cabins with
private bath attached In addition
there will be a great swimming bath
aboard both the Olympic and toe
Titanic large enough to perntlt of
diving A gymnasium the largest and
most completely equipped afloatt 1111
rII Kcq
be found on each of the new boats I
The main dining saloon Which wIll 1
seat moro than GOO passengers will I
be the largest single cabin on the ship
and In Its furnIshing and deco atlf11
the most elaborate Should a guest
tlro or this apartment In the week ho
Is at sea ho can wander from ono
cafe to another enjoYing practically
as much variety ns he might ashore
A veranda cafe will bo built on one
of the upper decks far astern looking
out over the sea and about fifty feat
above the water The decorations and
general management will carr out the
Idea of the openail cafes ot Southern
Eurore The cafe will be erected with
exposed rafters entwined with vines
and the sides will be latticed effects
to make the illusion of a cafe at the
seaside as complete as possible
Another novelty will be n Jrlll room
The cabin will suggest an old English
chop house with hlghbacled stalls of
ancient oak and broad low tables It
will be possible nt any hour of the day
or night for a passenger to use the
grill room The palm garden will be
still another refuge for those who
weary of the confines of the ship dur
ing the lall5age
A garden will be located on the sun
deck and 111 the winter months will bo
protected by a glass roof Here will
bo found perhaps the most complete
illusion or the hotel ashore There will
be arbors artfully contrived to give the
effect of gardens covered with vines
and lowers The chlldlens room ot the
new liners wlll be the most sumptuous
apartment or Its kind ever attempted
The new liners will be as complete In
their safety devices as In their luxuri
ous equipment Each boat will be di
vided Into upward or 30 steel compart
ments separated by heavy bulkheads
An automatic device on the bridge will
control all these heavy steel door
making It possible for a single hand to
close them all In case ot danger Each
of these doors In turn will be electric
ally connected with a chart on the
bridge and wIn be represented by small
electric lights When one or these
doors closes the light will burn red The
officer on the bridge will thus be ahl
to see at a lance If all of the com
partments are closed Still another set
or safety devices will guard against
fire In every part of the ship
A combination of turbine and recIpro
cating engines will propel the vessels
It Is expected that a great economy
or coal will be effected by this ar
rangement The berths In Harland
Volfs yards at Belfast In which
those wonderful ships arc being built
are each 1000 feet long and capable of
bearing a dead weight of i5OOO tons
The Olympic 15 expected to be ready for
launching In the early autumn of 1910
London Dally News</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1910-07-11/ed-1/seq-3/#words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>IFli; or NEW LINERS
SOON 10 BE LAUNCHED
Hr Carlisle Says Olympic and
" Titanic Will Be Handsomest
Vessels Afloat.
LiOMSTER.S OF 45.000 TONS
tvrert Says There Is No Reason
'•'■■7 They Should Not. Be
x \ Ha-^ ec * — — Praise
fin Americans.
, Vs rt r VT — ah!*' "Alexander M Car
'~*r r*""e^2^ 'Tir'l— ' Of the big shipbuild-.
i ' : r-r -\\ Z '"-•" -• Harlassd Wolff, at Belfast.
r%r^*£T.d probably the most • prominent
|g!Swj constructor in Great Britain, ar-
T^an yesterday en the .Whit* Star
»T^ r, .-- ,-.-?• of the vessels "which grew
*F, *£ o^servatioti in the Belfast yards.
i-T^ •"s-i-t bssb Bf about sixty, and has
.**^i-v tie Crsa he represents for forty;
**^~~ezzs According c his friends he is
f: _.."- ■ talks little, but. thinks much.
s .rCl crpt-ired —1? yesterday when he
j^**^v £ V about the new-, theusand-fect
c t2.r eiants that are seen to leave
Kr^,;^ Vt Belfast
**".-: -vT~s -=thir.g at all to say." said Mr
fejjsie iSraptly. '"- tm not S" c — to talk
S-TsSlps What "have" I com© over- for"
W--V2 SStle ?--- trip and the salt baths.
» *— rcirg right back en the Oceanic on
VfeSaai :
jri-ec - t-"- e £e2 - waase at Belfast was
J.. r -«t £5 coed se the salt water of the
r, J^ r of Vfeew York, Mr Carlisle replied :
■» s'-spese S! But you see I came over to
«^ 2*iitt2s» -- - at sea: to get the sea air
%i tie salt t-stis or. board the Celtic"
Cr tie : "'" '- tie bay -- Carlisle clung
v^c^v -- •£%' remark that he -would not
T ,v ajjsst ships, but he asksd many ques
.j.,., ibbct tie harbor and the cutters that
aX tie Celtic By degress v,«, warmed up
7. -_;* cibject o* stear^ship construction, to
•rt^zz. he hsi obßd his life, and declared
£2* -*- Clynplc and Titanic would but*
p^serSsenr ark -"--er- they cams here in
3£-
-- ..-tv, -»--rk or these big Etfiaisshlps is
rilTor. -.-:;-■ right and day," he "said,
— -j •?.«, "wd have the Olympic ready for
jssciis -— October Nothing can com
t--c with zs.ezz. in si;* and beauty You
rZI zit z. reflation. In rocm a^d decoratics
xtn. tbese -'cssels cc=s to *e-v York."
BiiMd bet PsMio Wants.
-- yz- bs^evs ■- *-ii:<*iz.r BBC* iarjre
£-=silps-
-Te. I SJ:- -- reascr Thy great liners
£oulc zct be Mscstreeted if the travelling
jcil;c is Tilling tc pay for transpertaticn
■ ~ij?e they net aswSeSfiy lather hard to
—- -t-A »r v PT» retti — g — 1 pert?"
?':• v. _.. replied >Xr. Carlisle, with
••c r-■"■;'---"r -■"■;'---" of a. frown. '"With --i
*—c~j'^ -. rzzszes can s^'ir.^ £ big liner
jj-mrfl ""rtth ease. Quadruple screws are
zz rrzzztr advantage As long as you
izTr ewe big propellers 90s can hand:?- s
blr siip. '.' is net a a-uestior of the num
ber of prrpeilers. bat the depth they are
.- the waxes They must have solid water
w •'•ori In You know- - 1 =• cannot always
-_..- £i:ps as we would like to build
r-.err. We ia--e tc b-uild the^n according to
*i£ depth cf the harbors they are re enter
I ■_-...-.: good •" ark has been done with the
■sr.:r:: Channel at ..this port. You
Ancri;ar:s are able people, and you can
"Ct--arythi^g yoa set your minds upon.- If
ysc wsat -.£ ships, are will build them
■•
'"To ywa believe in high speed like that
cf the Ururetar-ia -. - 1 the Losaftaals ' '
"That again is a Question for Che travel-
Utg pibSc If •'-..- people. "want to travel
fist they rinst expect to- pay for travelling
::_r. The Olympic and the Titanic will
zzve 2. sp^ed of ti ■cue knots That
is * rzzi iced for large ships. Ycu will
rse sc~e rc-sm -. those vessels The
rt^tfcrsoms -'-'111 be unusually large, ezsd
tier will te as abundance of room every
■"•isre. Fir example, we win have an ex
c^zzzliy large room off the. dining Bar
tons T-ie-r* people may meet before din-
Sar .;: bold receptlcns. The decoration?
Till be unsurpassed They will ' be the
frsr tliit money can buy They will not
s^rc bs the most magnificent, bui they
Tin i« th most substantial and solid that
«-ver -J-ere put tote a steamship."
If- Carlisle laughed when asked -what
isiarii cf the big Huropa. which the Hsm
lur?-American Lin© had contracted for
ti-rtly bifcirp- the recent financial panic in
' Tiev 2.r^ to have s. Sn? new vessel,"* he
f-ii* Kf an exceptionally ' big typ* Hsrr
Altrt Eallin. of the Hamburg-Am«*rican
lise, is 'd. marvellous nan He know? the
Ft^cnsiir. business He has done big
"rlrps, ar.d vQ] continue to fin big things. ■
; -fe 'Z th© best, ■ad I understand one of
.*"*£ Tzzrt profitable and popular, BtaMneb*ns
"tf~The Hamburg-American L'r:"=- is the
-a-hich -i-ec. built several years
~€~ in cur yards st Belfast.
Ciyrrcic Launching in the Fa!!.
Aricfci when the Olympic and the Titanic
"•xeli visit tbea»«atan Mr C^rliEl* said.
'""*•'?- win launch The Olympic in October
tzi she should be in service in tbe middle
r ~ ISCi. The vessels are so large and there
t'j much to be done an them after the
hww^fag that they car.not be sent out be-;
f-.-* that time the Titanic will probably
ft ready MSI three or four months after
"-'^ Olympic sails on her maiden passage "
"*-'.i6 is the first vacation Mr Carlisle has
h;f in three years. The work at th*- yards
its kept him there constantly since his
rir!t here res years ap» He pointed to
t-.'j Brooklyn Bridge on the way -up bay
.--• remarked that he went across it on
<•-«•. . - th. strands while it was in ceur?e
c! ccrstricticn. He expressed great Inter
'~' ;• the railroad terminal facilities in this
fcty, tnfl > stewed much praise on the 3c
*«ssraLtton and ability of Americans He
f ; *Slss oat .IP Morgan as on* of -Assert-.
c - ? ?reir men, who invariably did that
"^iJcS hf. kd planned to do
"*'- rz'r* raofat than 7*i,V^ tons in ccurs*
*"- wtstructtoji at Belfaßt,*" he said, "and
*" .t Ere -r- unusually busy ICe one
-■— lies ths great amount of work required
*'• bc!ld such big steamships 5? the
zr.i the Olympic. rbere '■ only
European
Visitors
• : npiran Columns
\i ' -York Tribune
a reliable £uidc to the best
Ebops, hotels and resorts.
Consult These Columns
Before Sailing
■ ' much valuable time will
be "saved for sightseeing.
sea ■"•a- q r£t 6ve " 2 fairt rr3 « of it,
—^ that Is for one to visit the yards.
To. Be Things of Bsauty.
**** too. the average person cannot
understand the tremendous amount of
ac-sey put Into ta« decoration Only an
■TOM or an architect can know the real
fceautv or understand the time and the
money required to make the interior* of
the big ships. Thus far there- I? hardly
anything that caa surpass the decorations
OB the Mauritania Be patient and watch
few the decorations on the. Olympic."
air. Carlisle -was employed at the Eel
35- yards when the first Oceanic of the
hit* Star Line was launched. When the
second Oceanic, now in port, was launched
MS left the -ways under hi? direction.
The Olympic and Titanic -will be 4S*V
ton vessels. They in called "thcusand
foof ships, but their length win be MO
fee* The new Hamburg: American liner
hot- under construction at Stettin will be
S?6 feet, -with a tonnage of 45. W. The
Msure-tar.ia. and the LuEitania are each "!*
feet in length . with a tonnage of 32.500
When it was announced last month in
London that the great docks -would be
constructed en the Mersey the Ctmard
L;?.!, it is said, planned to construct new
liters of 60.060 tons.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1911-05-31/ed-1/seq-5/#date1=05%2F31%2F1911&index=1&rows=20&searchType=advanced&language=&sequence=0&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>MONSTEB LINER LAUNCHED.
Steamer Titanic Slides Into Water
at Belfast.
BELFAST, May .11.?Enthusiastic
crowds lined the banks of the River
lagan and cheered lustily as the Whits
Star line's great steamer Titanic was
launched with appropriate ceremonies
this morning.
The Titanic will enter the White Star's
New York-Soutl^ampton service late in
the year, but her sister vessel Olympic
steams from . Southampton two weeks
hence for New York, and these two sea
monsters, each 45,000 tons register,
882Vt feet long and 92 H fo*t broad,
boast the distinction of being the
largest and finest, vessels in the world
These massive ships are also notable
for the enchanting beauty and the un
usual spaciousness of their passenger ac
commodations, and in first, second and
third class the greatest comfort is prom
ised. On both steamers swimming pools,
tennis and hand ball courts, and Turkish
and electric bath establishments ars
among the Innovations introduced for the
pleasure of the passengers.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86086633/1912-04-03/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=03%2F30%2F1912&sort=date&date2=04%2F03%2F1912&searchType=advanced&language=&sequence=0&index=18&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>TITANIC'S MAIDEN TRIP.
Sister Ship to the Olympic of White
Star Line Snls Next Week.
Lorn! on, April The gigantic new
st Mam-ship Titanic of thr White Star
line arrive. todoy at Setithamptt n
from the MinN of her bulkiers at H-l-
fast. She is to be marie re.iriy for herj
maitlen trip across the Atlantl , the
atnri al ertotch la scheduled for sVed.
Oaaday af next week. The Titanic is a
sister ship to the Olympic. 8he Is 0
leet hmg and has a d b placement of
r.o 000 tons. The travellmr Ust n the
bb ship will have coo names "Hi its
brt lass roll, in addition to 500 BOO
ot l i lass and third cabin oa -
sengt ts. To this will be adder, the
. n v oi sua makina a t ui tlo.tiiiK
pojsilatlon of mir1y t.ooe.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86058226/1912-04-10/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=03%2F30%2F1912&index=5&rows=20&searchType=advanced&language=&sequence=0&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>TITANTIC SAILS ON
HER FIRST VOYAGE
White Star Liner the Largest
Vessel that Ever Sailed
the Seas.
(National News Association)
LONDON, April 10. Carrying 1400
passengers the liner Titanic of the
White Star line, than which there is
no larger vessel afloat, sailed from
Southhampton today on her maiden
voyage bound for New York. The Tt
tanic which is of 45,000 tons displace
ment Is sister ship to the Olympic.
All the special suites of rooms in
stituted as an innovation in the Titan
ic were occupied when the passage be
gun. These suites consist of bed
rooms, sitting room, bath room, and
servant's room and have their own
private deck promenade isolated from
the rest of the ship and not overlooked
by any other passengers.
The Titanic also possesses another
new feature in its Louis XVI. restaur
ant. Her sister ship the Olympic, also
has this feature but on a smaller
scale. It proved so popular, however,,
that the White Star company decided
to have Jhe one on the Titanic greatly
enlarged. Adjacent to it is a special
reception room for the use of passen
gers taking meals in the restaurant.
The Titanic while its engineering
principal is the same as that of the
Olympic, is expected by experts on
navigation to make faster time than
the Olympic because of a slight dif
ference in the curvature of the propel
ler blades. .</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1912-04-18/ed-1/seq-12/#date1=1756&index=0&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BURING A "TITANIC" ADVENTURE AT SEA
</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1912-04-22/ed-1/seq-5/#date1=1756&index=1&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>DEATH IN HUSBANDS' ARMS BETTER THAN LIFE
ALONE FORTHESE HEROINES OP TfiE TITANIC "
, .
The Titanic heroines Mrs. H. J. Allison (above) and Mrs. Isadore
i Straus.
The quiet, smiling heroism of
two women stand pre-eminent
among the thrilling 'stories told
by Titanic survivors the love
that was greater than death as
displaved hy'MTS.wH. J: Allison of qI jonefiness.
Milwaukee and' Mrs. Isadore
Straus of lyew York., Bofh went
down with their husbands on the
Titanic, refusing rescue at the
cost of separation and after-life</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1912-04-22/ed-1/seq-4/#date1=1756&index=3&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>"I didn't see anyone flash Iny
money," he said. "I hear that
some millionaire is said to have
attempted to get himself, wife
and their servants in a boat, and
that he" wrote- bigj checks to the
crew, but I did not see anything
like that."
This is Vice President Frank-lin'-s
story of what happened in
the New Yosk; offices of the
.White Star:
"About twenty minutes to two
Monday morning I was awakened
by a reporter on the telephone
who told me they had just heard
the Titanic had sent out calls for
assistance. " ,
"The press association repeat
ed whqt the reporter told me. I
asked them if they couldn't hold
back the news until it was con
firmed. They told me it already
had gone out. .
"I sent a Macconigram to the
captain of the Olympic asking
him to get into communication
with the Titanic. I then told all
our people to report to -the of
fice. "I then received the report that
the Titanic had been struck- by an
iceberg and was sinking by the
head. It was a press dispatch.
"But we had no authentic in
formation. '
"At 3 a. m, we sent another
wireless to the Olympic, again
urging it to get into communica
tion with the Titanic.
"At 6 a. m. we sent another
message to the Olympic. At that
time we had. absolutely no mes
sage from the Titanic. mj j ,
"About 1 o'clock we 'got an
other message from Captain Had
dock that the Carpathia was in
attendance and had picked np
twenty of the Titanic's boats fill
ed with passengers.
"We told the public these were
mets rumors.
"About 3 p. m. Monday, we
sent a message to the Olympic
oraering it to reiay messages
from the Carpathia.
"About 6:27 p. m. we received
the following message:
" 'Carpathia reached Titanic's
position at daybreak, fioats and
wreckage only of Titanic. About
675 souls saed. CarpathiaVeturn
ing to New York.v
"It was signed Haddock, Cap
tain of the Olympic.
"1 telephoned to the directors,
including J. Pierpont Morgan,
and then gave, the news to the re
porters' .
Frankfin denied any censor
ship of the-wrrekss.
He said that he knew, nothing
of the Iifesaving devices on -the
Titanic, except that they were up
to the standard for ocean liners.
When pressed for the reasons
for getting Titanic's officers and
crew out of the country, Franlclin
declared that it was because sail
ors were sq "difficult to control."
He did not say if this also was
the reason for the desire of Mr.
Ismay, managing director, to get '
out of the countrv.
oO .
"Titanic was racing for Amer
ica to make a trip that would
Startle the world," says dis
patches. As usual, the dare-deviltry
costs fives of the innocent.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1912-04-25/ed-1/seq-27/#date1=1756&index=4&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>LINJERCALIFORNIAN WAS ALLOWED TO DRIFT IN ICE
FIELDSAPTAINTELLS WHY TITANIC iS GONE
The senate investigating com
mittee is spending much time try
ing to firrifcout if the officer of
the Titanic had received wireless
warnings of the ice ahead "before
the collision with the iceberg.
The senate committee need not
bother with thatquestrqn.
For at least one hour before the
Titanic struck the berg, she was
plowing through an icefield made
of hundreds of smajl floes, with
here and there a berg of moun
tainous size. '
No experienced mariner would
have driven his ship through such
an icefield at the rate of 21 knots.
The Titanic did drive through
at that rate.
Captain Edwin JSmitti was m
command of the Titanic.
i Captain Smith was an expe
rienced mariner. He had been at
sea for forty years. He wap
krfown among his associates as a
careful commander. He even
wa criticised by o$her captains
fdr being tpo careful.
Woujd, Captain Smith, unless"
acting Under the direct orders of
his owners, have taken such a
fearful chance of sending the 2,
200 souls aboard his -vessel to
their death?
He certainly would not, and it
remains only for the senajte com-,
jnittee to find out who among the
owners of the Titanic gave the
drders under which Captain
Smith acted. . .
Whoever gave that order is the
murderer of the 1,500 deacj of the
Titanic s -
' Here is the story "of Captain
Lord, of the Leyland liner Cali-
fornian, given by Captain Lord to
the United Press at Boston to
'day. This story is" the most direct
proof possible" of the criminal
recklessness of the speed of the
Titanic at the timeWf the colli
sion v
v It explains why the Titanic is
at the bottom of the Atlantic
while the Californian is safe in
port.
BY CAPTAIN LORD
Commander of the California
,fVVe were directly in the wake
of the Titanic the night' of ile
wreck. We were from 15 to"lSv
miles behind her. '
"The Titanic struck . between
ten and eleven o'clock. At six
o'clock we began running irito he
ice field. v
"Most of this was small ice
cakes from" one to five feet thick
and from one to five feersquare.
In this smail ice, however," were
some veritable mountains of ice.
"At times w were fdrced to
reverse the engines, float slowly
up to the larger bergs, and, when
thebow touched, them, start the
engines to push them out of the
.way. '
"We hid made about ten miles
this way when dark came down.
It came down very quickly. We N
stopped altogether, for the bergs
got larger every foot we went
"The ice field wasat least ten
miles square, and mayhave been
two or three times that size.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045487/1915-05-24/ed-1/seq-11/#date1=1756&index=5&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>GIRL WIDOW OF TITANIC HERO MAY WED
ANOTHER MILLIONAIRE
Mrs. Madeline Force Astor and Clarence H. Mackay Whose Engagement
, Is Rumored.
Is Mrs. Madeline Force Astor, i of the ""Titanic disaster, soon to be
widow of CoL John Jacob Astor, hero j come Mrs. Clarence H. Mackay?,
m
iitmiwimMMi</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1912-04-24/ed-1/seq-3/#date1=1756&index=9&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>
FIRST PHOTOGRAPH OF SCENES CONNECTED WITH THE TITANIC DISASTER
Authentic Pictures of Survivors and Their Arrival in New York City on the Rescue Ship Carpathia
— All photographs on this page are copyrighted by Underwood Underwood, New York.
THE SAN FR Ay CISCO CALL, WEDNESDAY, APRIL-24; 1912.
3</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86066870/1912-04-16/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=1756&index=14&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Whole World is Appalled in Face of the Greatest Sea Horror of Modern Times
THE DAILY SENTINEL.
VOL. XIX.
UNDER WAVES
1400 SLEEPING
HOPE ABANDONED EXCEPT
FOR THOSE ON “CARPATHIN”
Astor, Butt, Guggenheim, Straus and Many Other Notables Re
ported Among the Lost.—Storms Sweep to Death All
Who Remained on Wreckage.—History Af
fords No Parallel for This Disaster.
v AL Sr
The appalling magnitude of the wrecking of the liner Titanic is
little mitigated by the fragmentary information which filters in today.
The rescuing steamer Carpathia has 868 survivors on board, ac
cording to the latest news received at the White Star offices in New
York city. This increases the list of the saved by about 200 from the
number at first reported. But with the revised figures at hand, there
still remain 1,850 persons, composing passengers and crew of the Ti
tanic, who today are unaccounted for—apparently lost.
The hope that the steamers Virginian and Parisian of the Allen
line had picked up additional survivors was dispelled when the' wire
less station on Sable island gave cut the information that the Parisian
had picked up no survivors, and a wireless message from the captain
of the Virginian said: ‘“‘Arrived at scene of disaster too late to be of
service.”
The Carpathia is coming to New York slowly. She will be in wire
less communication with Sable Island tonight.
London, New York and Paris are grief stricken and overwhelmed
by the terrible disaster. Tearful crowds thronged the steamship offices
in all the cities, awaiting hour after hour for news.
Many prominent people of both continents are among the miss
ing. No word has been received of Colonel John Jacob Astor, although
his wife is known to have been saved. Alfred G. Vanderbilt was not
on the Titanic, as at first reported. Isador Straus, the New York mill
ionaire merchant and philanthropist, who was on board, is not reported
among the survivors,
Associated Press.
New York, Apr. 16.—Brief wireless dispatches show that the pas
sengers and crew passed through thrilling experiences from the mo
ment the monster Titanic crashed into an iceberg in the dead of night
until the steamer Carpathia, several hours later, reached the scene and
rescued the survivors from lifeboats floating in a sea of ice.
The collision occurred at a timc when the passengers had retired
or were about to go to bed for the night, and the tremendous shock
oi the collision caused many of the passengers to rush to the decks
only partly dressed.
At once the passengers were ordered to the lifeboats, and many
were only scantily clad as they took their places in the boats. This
would indicate that the condition of the Titanic was such that there
was no time to return to the state rooms for additional clothing. Dan
ger confronted even those who were fortunate enough to be put into
the lifeboats.
Huge quantities of field ice covered the ocean, and in the dark
ness the crews had to guide the boats with the greatest care in order
to avoid being jammed and overturned. The ice was so heavy that
the crews could not keep the boats together and they were widely
separated. The air was biting cold and the chill breezes from the ice
floes caused the passengers to huddle together to keep warm. Through
out the night the lifeboats bobbed helplessly among the cakes of ice.
Shortly after 2 o'clock the sinking Titanic made a great dive into
the sea, carrying hundreds of persons to their death.
Finally daylight came, and with it arrived the Cunard Line steam
er Carpathia, which found only a score of lifeboats, filled with shiver
ing people, driving helplessly aboutthe vicinity where the Titanic had
gone undex the waves.
Associated Press.
St. Johns, N. F., Apr. 16, 3:45 p.m—All hopes of saving any of
the passengers or crew of the Titanic, other than those who are now on
board the Carpathia, have been abandoned this afternoon. All of the
steamers which had been cruising near the scene of the disaster have
continned on their voyage.
Associated Press.
Paris, Apr. 16.—The White Star Line office is besieged by weep
ing women, several of whom have scns on board. Among these were
Miys. William Dulles, who collapsed from the strain.
It has been established that Lady Duff Gordon, well known in Par
is as Lucille, the name under which she conducts a dressmaking busi
ness, sailed on the Titanic with her husband, Sir Cosmo Edmund Duff
tGordon. They appear on the passenger list as Mr. Morzan and wife
Robert Bacon, the United States ambassador to France, with his
wife and daughter, had planned to sail on the Titanic: but delay in
the arrival of Myron T. Herrick, his successor, caused Mr. Bacon to
postpone his departure.
Associated Press. = : 2
New York, Apr. 16.—Particulars as to the life-saving equipment
of the Titanic are not available, but her sister ship. the Olympic, has
16 lifeboats and 4 rafts. calculated to accommodate 1,171 persons. This
means about one-third the total number of the passengers and crew.
Established 1893,
EXCLUSIVE AFTERNOON ASSOCIATED PRESS REPORT
GRAND JUNCTION, COLORADO.
which ordinarily is 3,447, can be accommodated.
It is said that no ship is required to have sufficient boat room to
accemmodate the complete passenger and crew list.
Associated Press.
Halifax, N. S, Apr. 16.—The Parisian steamed through much of
the heavy field ice looking for passengers of the Titanic: but no rafts
or bodies were sighted among the fleating wreckage, which covered a
wide area.
The Parisian reports that the weather is so cold that, even if any
persons were on the wreckage, they probably would have perished from
exposure before they could have bern picked up.
The Parisian is expected to arrive here tomorrow morning.
Associated Press.
St. Johns, N. F., Apr. 16.—Mcssages from Cape Race indicate that
a large majority of the men on tle Titanic went down with the ship
Messages received from the C:rpathia state that all the boats that
were launched from the Titanic h: ve been accounted for.
The boats were filled largely with women and children; but had
a sufficient number of the Titanics crew to guide them.
The belief is general here that all who survived are on the Car
pathia.
Associated Press.
New York, Apr. 16.—Intense interest centers in the approach of
the Carpathia bearing the survivors of the Titanic. This ship promises
to bring the first authentic details of t\u great tragedy and the scenes
that followed. E N AR LT e T
The Carpathia is a slow vessel and is due to arrive at Sandy Hook
at 11 o'clock Thursday night.
Associated Press,
London, Apr, 16.—The crowds around the White Star Line offices
increased every moment this morning. The busses and carriages were
so thick that late comers were unable to get within several blocks of
the offices.
Associated Press.
Washington, Apr. 16.—Senator Simon Guggenheim of Colorado in
a telephone conversation with the White Star office in New York was
unable to learn the fate of his brother, Benjamin Guggenheim, who is
reputed to be one of the wealthiest men in the world. So far as can be
learned, his wife did not accompany him on the trip.
Associated Press.
New York, Apr. 16.—1 n the long roll of marine tragedies, that
which overtook the Titanic is the first instance on record wherein a
conspicuous vessel has met disaster on her maiden voyage. The nearest
approach is the case of the Naronic, which belonged to the same line
She went to the port of missing ships on her second voyage. Carrying
about 300 persons all told, she steemed out of this port on her return
trip nearly 20 years ago, and since then there has never been word
as to how she met her fate.
Associated Press.
Washington, Apr. 16.—A quick report from the White Star line
as to the number of lifeboats and lifc rafts carried by the Titanic has
been telegraphed for by Supervising Inspector Upler of the government
steamboat inspection service.
Associated Press.
New York, Apr. 16.—The off‘cial announcement that there are 868
survivors on board the Carpathia, and the fact that the names of only
315 of the saved have been sent in by wireless indicates that there
are 553 persons saved whose names were not included.
Associated Press.
Washington, Apr. 16.—Presid-nt Taft has directed that two reve
nue cutters be sent to meet the Carpathia. The scout cruiser Salem
which has the strongest wireless equipment in the navy, will also meet
the Carpathia and gather the namcs of the survivors.
A complete list of the survivors, likewise of the dead, will not be
available for days.
Associated Press,
New York, Apr. 16, 10:30 a.m.—Messages received here shortly
after 10 o'clock by Marconi wireless from Cape Race and Sable island
say that none of the Titanic's passengers are on board the Parisian or
the Virginian.
Associated Press.
London, Apr. 16.—The underwriters at Lloyd's are staggered by the
news: but it is declared that the insurance on the Titanic is so evenly
distributed that none of the underwriters are likely to be hard hit.
The reassuring cable dispatches of yesterday had sent the re-insur
ance rate down to 25 per cent, and the underwriters closed up at night
hopeful that all was well. Whed the offices re-opened this morning a
little business was done at 90 guineas, but the rate quickly raised to
95, which is known as the total-less rate.
It is estimated that, together with her cargo, the Titanic would
represent a loss of approximately 12,500,000 pounds. Of this 750.000
pounds is retained by the White Star Steamship Company at their own
risk and the balance is placed on the insurance market in London, Liv
erpool, Hamburg and elsewhere.
Associated Press. ‘
New York, Apr. 16. 11 a.m —Captain Rostron of the Carpathia
sent a wireless message this morning ‘saying that the Carpathia, with
BCO survivers of the Titanic on board, was proceeding slowly toward
New York through the field of ice. :
55—
TUESDAY, APRIL 16, 1912,
50c Per Month.
FRaT AGGURATE DETAILS
OF THE AWFUL DISASTER
Life-Saving Facilities Being Limited, Men on Board the Titanic
Gave Way to Women and Children, and Bravely Went
fo Their Death.—With a Fearful Lurch the
Yessel Sank to the Bottom, ¥
Associated Press.
New York, Apr. 16, 4 p.m.—Vice President Franklin of the White
Star line has been criticised today for his reassuring declarations of yes*
terday, tending to mislead the public.
This afternoon he made public the full text of the wireless mes
sages received from Captain Haddock of the Olympic yesterday after
noon.
“The reason I did not give it out last night," Mr. Franklin said.
“was because it was so discouraging that I thought it would not be
right to alarm the public unnecessarily. Now that the worst is known,
I am willing to give it out. It is as follows:
** ‘Carpathia reached Titanic's position at daybreak. Found boats
and wreckage only. Titanic had fcundered about 2:20 a.m. in 41.16
north, 50.14 west. All the boats accounted for. About 675 souls saved,
crew and passengers. Latter nearly all women and children. Leyland
line steamship Californian remainirg and searching exact position of dis
aster. Carpathia returning to New York with survivors. Please inform
Cunard. (Signed) ‘HADDOCK.' "
Associated Press.
New York, Apr. 16, 4 p.m.—Of the 3,423 bags of mail on the Ti
tanic about 200 sacks contained registered matter. Postmaster Morgans
says that these sacks contained on an average of 8,000 letters each. Hao
estimated that 16,000 registered letters and packages had gone to the
bottom,
Associated Press.
Washington, Apr. 16, 5 p.m.—Senator Guggenheim said this after
ncon that he had received advices from the White Star line that all
but 32 of the first-cabin passengers on the Titanic are safe.
Associated Press.
Washington, Apr. 16, 4:3¢ pm.—The White House is gloomy to
day, as Major Butt's name is not among the survivors received.
“The chance is a slim one; hut we are holding to that,” said Pres
ident Taft to a friend as he departed for lunch.
Associated Press,
Havre, France, Apr. 16, 3:30 p.m.—The Presse Nouvelle quotes
the captain of the French liner La Touraine as saying that he had sent
a wireless dispatch, reporting the presence of icebergs, to the captain of
the Titanic and that the latter acknowledged the message with thanks.
Associated Press.
New York, Apr. 16, 5 p.m.—Vice President Franklin of the White
Star line said at 4:50 this aftern on that 202 out of the 325 first
cabin passengers and 114 out of the 225 second-cabin passengers of
the Titanic had been accounted for
Associated Press.
Philadelphia, Pa., Apr. 16, 4:15 p.m—Six of the 53 Philadelphi
ans on the Titanic are unaccoynttd for. They include George Widner
and his son, Harry Elkins Widener. Mr. Widener is a son of P. A. B.
Widener, a Philadelphia capitalist. Mrs, Widener was saved.
Among the rescued are J. B. Thayer, second vice president of the
Pennsylvania railroad, and his wife and son.
Associated Press.
New York, Apr. 16.—All through the night the offices of the
White Star Line company and the newspapers were besieged by per
sons who were eager to know of the safety of friends or relatives on
the Titanic, while a flood of telegiams, cablegrams and telephone mes
sages were received.
The wireless telegraph operators worked through the night, try
ing to pick up calls from the scene of the disaster. The wireless was
handicapped by a thunder storm which finally silenced all transmission
for a time,
President Taft telegraphed, asking information of his military aide,
Major Archibald W. Butt, and was promised the earliest tidings that
should come in.
According to wireless messages received here, the Carpathia will
arrive in New York Thursday afternoon.
The treasury officials have decided to waive the customs regula
tions in order that the landing of everybody may be facilitated.
Associated Press.
Meontreal, Que., Apr. 16.—The weather signal station on the Gulf
of St. Lawrence reported today that heavy fogs are lying off the coast
of Nova Scotia, and that a violent thunder storm broke in that neioh-
B R e L R R e s To PR WL . Rt AR ¥ LI
(Continued on Page Four.)</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn92066979/1912-04-20/ed-1/seq-1/#date1=1756&sort=relevance&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>SERVICES ON SUNDAY
IN ALL THEXHURCHES
BY COMMON CONSENT TOMOR
ROW TO BE DEVOTED IN PUL
PITS OF COUNTRY IN
PRAYER FOR VICTIMS
Titanic Tragedy Presents Picture
Without Precedent of Bravery of
Impulse, Unstudied, Unassuming
and Instinctive, Alike in Steerage
Passenger, Stoker and Millionaire
—True Tales Neber Told.
New York, April 20. —Nearly a week
has passed since the Titanic, greatest
marine achievement in the history of
the world, sank in mid-ocean. Much
of her story still is untold, and many
a day will pass before the world will
fully comprehend the significance of
the disaster.
The number of dead probably will
never be exactly determined, inas
much as the complete passenger list
went down with the vessel. The num
ber of survivors is fixed at 705 by the
report of Captain Rostron of the Car
pathia. Tbe White Star line officials
believe the death list totaled approxi
mately 1,635.
Day of Sorrow Tomorrow.
The narratives, gathered piecemeal
from the liner’s survivors, pay a trib
ute without precedent to the bravery
of the men and women of these mod
ern days, a bravery of impulse, un
studied, unassuming and instinctive,
alike in steerage passenger, stoker
and millionaire. By common consent
the churches of the world will set
aside their pulpits tomorrow for a
reverent consideration of the disaster
and for mourning for the lost.
Provision for the Living.
As to the needs of the living, am
p’.e provision is rapidly being made.
The relief funds being gathered in
New York and London already total
well up in the hundreds of thousands.
Most of the steerage passengers who
reached New York distraught and
penniless have already come to realize
the generosity and hospitality of
America. Clad, fed and housed, they
will be given ample time to recover
from the shock of their experience and
will stajt their life in the new world
with ample funds and kindly advice
of excellent counsellors.
Story of Vessel's Fate.
The most complete story of the Ti
tanic’s fate yet obtained is being rap
idly gathered in New York by the
members of the Senate investigating
committee. The committee has al
ready listened to the testimony of J.
Bruce Ismay, managing director of
the White Star line; Captain Rostron
of the Carpathla, Charles W. Light
holder, second officer of the Titanic,
and others. The witnesses for today’s
session include H. J. Pittman, third
officer of the Titanic; J. G. Roxhol,
fourth officer; G. Lowe, also in an of
ficial position on the Titanic, and fif
teen of the crew.
The committee has the assistance
of George Uhler, chief of the United
States steamboat inspection service, (
and Truman H. Newberry, who was I
secretary of the navy under Theo-|
dore Roosevelt.
Thought Vessel Unsinkable.
The burden of testimony presented (
emphasizes the unquestioning faith of
the Titanic officers in her unsinkable
character, the recklessness of steam
ing full speed through a sea where
dangerous icebergs were known to
threaten and the remarkable calm- (
ness of passengers and crew. The Ti-|
tanic’s fa’e already has resulted ii
action by the trans-Atlantic lines to
insure liners taking a course far *.o i
the south, where the iceberg danger (
will no longer be present. The linos,
it is announced, have agreed on a new
“long” course, which dips far to the
south of the Titanic's course. There
is little disposition to criticise. Cap
tian Smith for following the ocean
lane in which he met disaster. He
showed caution, according to the na-1
val hydrographers, in steering a
course well to the south of the regular
southern lane.
The Northern Course.
The northern course, used by ves- 1
seis from July to January, crosses the
grand banks in latitude 45 north, four
degrees further north than the south
ern or “long course,” In which the
MEMBER OB THE: ASSOC IATED rr ESS
- Titanic met its fate. The Titanic was
sixty miles south of the regular south
ern course and was even in danger of
collision with east-bound steamers.
The new route eastbound provides
that steamships shall dip to latitude
» 38.20 on the first third of their course,
f making a total distance from New
York to Fastnet of 3,000 miles, where
J the distance now’ is reckoned at 2,858
5 1 miles. The loss of time on the new
s course will be about nine hours for a
24-knot boat. Boats of the Olympic
class may be eleven or fourteen hours
longer in crossing. They will gain,
• however, in having clear weather
t most of the time, avoiding delays from
f fog. There w r as some criticism among
i the ’survivors here of the Titanic
’ crew’s inability to handle the life
l boats.
No Boat Drills.
Albert Major, stewart on the Titan
l ic, admitted that there had been no
• boat drills and that the lifeboats
- were poorly handled.
“One thing comes to my mind above
! all else,” he said. 4, We of the crew
■ realized at the start of the trouble
1 that we were unorganized] and al
thought every man did his best, w’e
were hindered in getting the best re
sults because w’e could not pull to
-1 gether. There had not been a single
boat drill on the Titanic.”
Story By a Fireman.
One story, told by a fireman, runs.
“The engineers stayed by the pumps
and went down with the ship. The
firemen and stokers were sent on deck
five minutes before the Titanic sank,
when it was seen they would inevit
ably be lost if they stayed longer at
their work of trying to keep the fires
in the boilers and the pumps at work.
The lights burned to the last because
the dynamos were run by oil engines.”
With the sailing of a majority of
the Titanic’s crew on the Lapland
some sources of interesting informa
tion have been closed until the Red
Star liner reaches the other side.*
United States Senator Smith believes
certain members of the crew’ that he
held here for examination may reveal
just what happened to the Titanic be
low decks when she struck the berg.
Second Officer Lightholder says the
Titanic did not break in two, but
made her dive diagonally into the
sea, and that when half way under
there were two explosions, which he
believes were boilers.
Survivors Doing Nicely.
The survivors in the hospitals are
reported to be doing nicely. Contri
butions to the survivors’ relief fund
continue to pour in. and more than fif
ty thousand dollars has been rai/ed.
Happy were the members of the
Titanic’s surviving crew as they pre
pared to depart on the Lapland. Gen
erous merchants and others had fitted
them out with clothing, hats, brushes,
razors and other things, together with
money for their immediate needs. Oth
er money will be sent later by the
relief committees.
Ismay Is Angry.
J. Bruce Ismay discussed with in
t terviewers the work of the Senate
• investigating committee, which he
I characterizes as “brutally unfair.” He
J said: “I cannot understand this sen-
I atorial inquiry. They are going at it
( in a manner that seems unjust, and
the injustice lies heaviest upon me.
Why, I cannot even protect myself by
’ having my counsel ask questions.
Don’t misunderstand me by thinking
1 mean questions calculated to twist
.witnesses up; on the contrary, ques
tions tending to simplify involved
meanings.”
Has Clear Conscience.
Discussing his departure from the
Titanic, Mr. Ismay said:' “1 have
searched my mind with deepest care.
I have thought, long over each single j
incident that I could recal). I am •
sure that 1 did nothing that I should
not have done. My conscience is clear, |
and I have not been a lenient judge
of my acts.
Chance Came to Him.
“I tell you that if I thought that in
the slightest way I had done any
j wrong I would never have another
; happy moment. I took the chance of <
1 escaping when it came to me—l did [
not seek it. Every woman and child
had been cared for before I left the
boat. 1
• “And more, all the men within reach
LARAMIE, WYOMING, SATURDAY, APRIL 20, 1912.
had been taken care of before I took
my turn. And why shouldn’t I take
my turn? There are only two classes
on ship—the crew and the passengers.
I was a passenger.
“It is true 1 am president of the
company, but I didn’t consider myself
any different from the rest of the pas
sengers, 1 took no other man’s place.”
J. Bruce Ismay and other officials
of the White Star line were sub
poenaed today by the Senate investi
gating committee to appear before it
in Washington Monday. The investi
gation in New York will be concluded
today.
LITTLE GIRL DIES.
Stood With Captain on Bridge When
the Titanic Went Down.
New York, April 20.—Taking refuge
on the bridge of the ill-fated Titanic,
two little children remained by the
side of Captain Smith until that por
tion of the big ship had been swept
under w’ater. Survivors of the crew
who went down with the Titanic but
were saved by clinging to an overturn
ed lifeboat today told of their gallant
commander’s effort to save the life of
one of the children. He died a sail
or’s death and the little girl who had
entrusted her life to his care died
with him.

ISMAY AND WIRELESS
OPERATORS TESTIFY
ARE TELLING CONNECTION WITH
j THE DISASTER WHICH RE
SULTED IN THE SINKING
OF THE TITANIC.
President Ismay Says That He is on
Point of Nervous Collapse, But
Was Not Permitted to Retire—
Wireless Operators Recite Their
Deeds Aboard the Carpathla After
Picking Up of Titanic Victims.
G New York, April 19. —Appear- O
<3 ing before the Senate Titanic in- O
O vestlgatlng committee in a O
G wheel chair Harold Bride, assis- G
Q taut wireless operator of the 111- Q
Q facer ship who was disabled in O
G the rescue, testified today that al- O
U though the North German Lloyd: 0
O liner Frankfurt was twenty O
Q miles neared the Titanic than the 0
O Carpathla, no effort was made to 0
Ogave h<?r news of the Titanic’s O
O sinking condition. Bride testified O
0 that Phillips, the chief wireless O
O operator, told the Frankfurt wire- o
O less man he was a tool and better 0
O keep out. The Frankfurt, he 0
O said, was first to answer the Ti- O
O tanic’s signals of distress. The O
G reason no details were given the 0
O the German ship. Bride said, was O
0 that they believed her operator 0
O could not understand. O
O Bride also testified to having Q
O received warning of Icebergs in O
O the vicinity and to having deliv- O
O ered them to his superior officers, o
O one to Captain Smith himself. O
90000000000000000
ISMAY HEARD.
Officers of White Star Line Clear Up
Several Points.
New York, April 20— J. Bruce Is
may, managing director of the White
Star line, is to be recalled before the
Senate investigating committee now
delving ifito J|ie facts surrounding the
wreck of the Titanic. He probably
will be summoned io testify in rebut
tal before the day’s testifying is over,
according to Senator Smith of Michi
gan, chairman of the committee, who
acknowledged this morning that it
was the intention of the committee
to have the White Star line’s chief
executive again before it for the pur
pose of clearing up several poin's that
now appear to be in dispute by wit
nesses.
Wanted to Be Excused.
Although Mr. Ismay urged the com
mittee to permit him to go for the
present, pleading that he was on the
verge of a nervous collapse by reason
of his experiences, his request was
I not granted. There will remain as
witnesses four officers and twelve
1 members of the crew and they will be
heard as quickly as possible. The in
dications are that the inquiry will not
be completed before the middle of
next week. Just before the Senate
committee investigating the Titanic
disaster me', an invalid chair was
wheeled into the committee room, tn
it was Harold Bride, the assistant
wireless- operator on the Titanic,
whose feet were wrenched and badly
injured when he was crushed in the
liferaft that picked him up. He was
sallow and hollow-cheeked and lay
propped up with pillows awaiting his
call to the witness chair.
Will Add Lifeboats.
Immediately behind Bride came J.
Bruce Ismay, president of the Inter
national Mercantile Marine, and P. A.
S. Franklin, vice president of Ihe or
ganization. Mr. Ismay announced be
fore the inquiry began that ho had
given instructions to all the lines of
the Interna'lonal Mercantile, Marine,
which Include the White Star, the
American Red Star, the Leland, the
Atlantic Transport and the Dominion
lines, to equip all steamers with suf
ficient lifeboats and raft boats f>r
every passenger and every man of
the crew, without regard to govern
ment regulations.
Operator on Stand.
The first witness was Thomas Cot
tam, the wireless operator on the Car
pat hia, who was recalled to the stand.
Senator Smith sought to clear up the
TEN PAGES
messages that had passed between
the Carpathla and the Titanic.
What was the last message sent
to the Titanic?" asked Senator Smith.
"We sent It word to have its life
boats ready," said the witness; "that
our lifeboats were ready and that we
were steaming to them as fast as we
could."
Keeping Back the News.
Senator Smith asked a question to
discover whether any official had
sought to keep back news of the dis
| aster.
"Did you send any message that all
the passengers had been saved or that
the Titanic was being towed to Hali
fax?"
"No, sir."
"Nor anything like it?”
“No, sir.”
"Did you know such reports were
being published, to the world?”
“No, sir."
"If the White Star line sent a mes
sage Monday reading: ‘Representa
tive J. H. Hughes, Huntington, W. Va.;
Titanic proceeding to Halifax; passen
gers probably will land there Wed
nesday; all safe,’ they did not obtain
the information on which that is bas
ed from you?"
“No."
“Nor do you know that it obtained
it from any other operator on the Car
pathia?"
“No.”
Senator Smith asked the witness if
he had received a message from the
time the Carpathla left the scene of
the disaster until it reached New
York.
“No, sir,” answered Cottam. "I re
ported the entire matter myself to the
steamship Baltic at 10:30 o’clock Mon
day morning. I told them we had
been to the wreck and had picked up
as many of the passengers as we
could.”
Much Sleep Lost.
Cottam repeated his testimony of
yesterday and said he had been with
out sleep throughout Sunday, Monday,
Tuesday and until late Wednesday aft
ernoon. Senator Smith sought to have
the witness designate the exact hour
when he was relieved by Operator
Bride, who had been taken aboard the
Carpathla from the Titanic.
“I don't know, sir,” said Cottam in
extenuation. "1 was up continuously
and I lost track of the hours and days.
I had from eight to ten hours sleep
from the time we left the wreck until
we arrived In New York.
“Did Bride do any sending in that
time?" Senator Smith asked.
"Yes sir. He sent the list of the
third-class passengers to the cruiser
Chester.”
"Any other message?"
“Several; I don’t remember what
they were. The records are on the
Carpathla."
"Did you or Bride send any message
declaring that the Titanic was being
towed into Halifax?"
“No, sir,” said the witness, with
emphasis.
Titanic Operator.
Senator Smith then called what he
evidently expected to be one of the
most important witnesses, Harold S.
Bride, the sole surviving wireless op
erator of the Titanic. Crippled as a
result of his experiences, he was
wheeled in an invalid’s chair to the
table where the committee sat.
“Contrary to the usual procedure,”
said Mr. Smith, “I must place you un
der oath.”
Bride remembered receiving and
sending messages regarding the speed
lof the Titanic on its trial tests. After
leaving Southampton on the Titanic’s
fatal trip, he could not remember re
ceiving or sending any messages for
Ismay.
| After testifying that he had made
no permanent record of the iceberg
warnings, Bride insisted he gave tin;
memorandum of the warning to the
officer on watch. The nam'e of the of
ficer he could not tell.
I "1 know the officers by sight but
not by name," he said. Ho did not in
. form Captain Smith. Bride said he
saw Phllllppß in the operating room.
Told of Injury to Boat.
' “He told me he thought tbe boat
had been Injured In some way and
(Continued on Page Five.)</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1912-04-28/ed-1/seq-75/#date1=1756&sort=relevance&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>A Graphic, Continuous Tale of the First
and Only Voyage of the Bi??est
Ship in the World That Ended
So Disastrously Off the Great Ji
Newfoundland Banks.
The Hymn That the Ship's Band
Played r % the Vessel Went Down.
The Captain and Officers of the Titanic.?From Left to Right, Dr. W. F.
N. O'Laughlin, H. T. Wilde, Chief Officer; Chief Engineer Fleming;
Purser McElray.?Seated, Capt. E.J. Smith.
Now that the first shock of the Ti
tanic disaster, with the succession of
wild rumors which it brought, has
given place to something like certain
knowledge of what occurred on the
terrible night that the giant liner
plunged to the bottom of the sea, the
following complete narrative of the
wreck, with the events that preceded
and followed It, is rendered most time
ly. With Its swift alternations of
scenes of horror and heroism, of grim
struggles for life and awful suffer
ings, It is probably the most dramatics
true story of the sea ever written.
It is printed at the request of many
readers.
THE giant Titanic of the White
Star Line, the biggest ship afloat
when she sailed from Southamp
ton, England, on April 10, on her
maiden voyage to the Port of New
York, lies to-day a broken wreck, 2,760
fathoms beneath the ocean's surface,
some 800 miles from shore off the
great Newfoundland Banks. The ship
that was unsinkable, In the minds of
her leakers and the men that ran her,
has been sunk. The Queen of the Seas
is less to-day than one of her lifeboats
which bobs up and down on the broken
surface of the Hudson River, safe be
tween the piers of the White Star Line.
And in her sinking the Titanic ex
acted greater toll than humanity ever
before had been made to pay for Its ef
forts to conquer the sea. Of the 2,340
persons composing passengers and crew
of the big liner, only T05 over reached
this port. More than two-thirds of
those who embarked on the Titanio for
her maiden Journey?1,635 persons ex
actly?went down with her when she
snubbed her nose beneath the waves,
hung, quivering an instant, half above
and half below the surfaco, and then
started her downward plunge to the
bottom, nearly two miles bolow.
Since then the cable ships Mackay
Bennett and Mlnla have been pt the
scene of the wreck searching for bldies.
Some have been identified by articles
In the clothing and are now on their
way to Halifax aboard the Mackay
Bennett. Altogether 205 liad been picked
up last Thursday, The steamship Is
due there this morning. Others were
recommitted to the sea after it had
been found that they were unrecogniza
ble. The Minia will remain at the
scene of the disaster for some days to
come, and it will not be until there Is
a fair certainty that everybody recov
erable has been found that the search
will be abandoned.
It was collision wltji an iceberg which
caused the destruction of the Titanic,
and thoee who would moralise over the
great ship's loss can see in such a meet
ing the hand of Fate, which required
the greatest example of man's handi
work afloat on the sea to point its
protest against his ambition. For It
seems certain that nothing less than an
Iceberg could have withstood collision
with the enormous Titanic. Than her
no ship which sails the seas 'riras better
prepared to meet unexpected encoun
ters with others. Even a war vessel,
the heaviest Dreadnought, probably
must have succumbed to the rushing
Impetus of the monster Titanic had
they Jostled each other In the narrow
lanes of the ocean.
It had to be something greater than
any ship afloat to sink the Titanic, and
that something was supplied In the
tremendous berg, eight-ninths of whose
bulk skulked beneath the waves while
it presented a paltry lump of Ice, some
120 feet in height to do combat with
the steamship.
It Is thirteen days since the Ti
tanic sank?fourteen since she plunged
into the berg. Through many of those
days her owners and those who waited
ashore for news of dear ones aboard
the big liner were forced to be con
tent with meagre wireless accounts
Of the accident. In the Titanic's
passenger list were such names as Col.
and Mrs. John Jacob Astor, Major
Archibald Butt, military aid to Presi
dent Taft; James Clinch Smith. Dr.
Washington Dodge, Assessor of Port,
San Francisco; Mrs. Dodge and child.
Sir Cosmo and Lady Duff-Gordon.
Charles M. Hays, President of the
Grand Trunk Pacific of Canada, his
wife and daughter; W. T. Stead. Ben
jamin Guggenheim, F. D. Millet, the
artist; G. D. Widener of Philadel
phia, Countess Rothes, Mr. and Mrs
Isidor Straus. J. B. Thayer, Vlce^l^resl
dent of the Pennsylvania Railroad, his
wife and son; T. D. M. Cardeza, Clar
ence Moore of Washington, Robert W.
Daniels of Philadelphia, J. Bruce
Ismay, President of the International
Mercantile Marine Company, owner of
the line; Henrv B. Harris, the theatrl- j
cal manager, and Mrs. Harris: Thomas
Andrews, designer, and Archie Frost,
Chief Engineer for Harland & Wolff
the Titanic's builders.
Many of these and of the others
aboard the Titanic had postponed or
advanced their dates of sailing from
Europe, In some instances paying large
bonuses, for the privilege of making
the Titanic's maiden voyage. For
many of these passengers there was in
terest felt ashore, and inquiries were
made not ohly by members of their
families and by friends, but by persons
connected with them in business or
whose fortunes would be Influenced by
their life or death.
For such anxious Inquirer*) there were
many hours of suspense before even a
partial and Inaccurate list of the sur
vivors was wirelessed ashore from the
Cunarder Carpathla which rescued all
of the Titanic's passengers who were
saved. From this, lists of those who
had gone down with the steamship were
devised, and later, when bodies were
found floating on the scene of the
wreck, lists of those who had been
identified were made.
Meantime t the Carpathla, most anx
iously awaited of all ships which were
nearing the Port of New York,
brought In her cargo of surviv
ors, and with them the first au
thentic story of the wreck, of how
the great ship had struck, of what oc
curred aboard her after her bottom
plates had been ripped off by contact
with the Iceberg and her fifteen water
tight compartments had begun to fill,
of how the order was given to take to
the boats and of how It was fulfilled,
of the conduct of officers and crew and
of passengers, especially that of those
whose names were famous throughout
the world; of how the lifeboats were
launched and of the long hours of wait
ing in these cockleshells while the Car
pathla was steaming at extraordinary
speed from many miles away. News of!
all this the Carpathla brought, but
mostly It was told by rescued passen
gers, still too excited to give more than i
impressionistic accounts of what had
befallen the giant ship and them.
The stories varied widely and in their
variances revealed how different may
be the impressions received in different
minds by the one occurrence. In the
main features the recollections of a
majority agreed. In detail they dif
fered, one from the other, as the imag
ination of one who recounted them dif
fered in quality from that of another.
It was not until the United States
Senate undertook an inquiry "into the
cause of the disaster that testimony
was obtained from which the actual
facts of the Titanic's sinking' could be
gathered. That inquiry is still under
way. As yet no blame has been fixed
for the worst marine catastrophe in re
corded history, but facts have been
brought out in the testimony of offi
cers of the ship, in the tales-of sur
vivors. and in the records of wireless
messages, sent and received, from
which an accurate account of the loss
of the Titanic, of the circumstances of
her encounter with the berg, of the ef
forts made to save the ship, and of the
death of the many and the savin* of a
few, can be constructed.
11 ?
THE FATAL VOYAGE
Lasted Just Five Days and Ended
Two Miles Beneath Atlantic's 8urface
HE TITANIC sailed from South
I ampton, England, on Wednes
JL day, April 10. Scarcely "had she
drawn out of her berth when
she narrowly escaped collision with the
American liner New York, which was
yanked from her moorings, her haw
sers snapped, by the tremendous suc
tion exerted by the new steamship. The
great Titanic drew the New York to
ward her as an iron filing is drawn to
a magnet, and the smaller vessel float
ed, helplessly, stern first, down on the
giantess of the seas.
Her passengers lined her decks on the
side off which the New York lay,
laughing with pride that they were
aboard such a ship, when they learned
that it was the Titanic's suction which
had strained the New York from its
moorings. That the narrowly avoided
collision was prophetic of that other
collision in which the Titanic was to
play the part of the pigmy could not
have entered the mind of a single per
son aboard.
Then the big steamship gathered
headway again, moving slowly while
she was in range of other shipping,
that the occurrence of the New York
might not be repeated, but increasing
her speed as she left the shore behind
until finally she was racing through
ocean waves, cleaving to a line which
her navigators had lain down for her,
off at last on her maiden Journey with
New York as her goal.
" News of her starting was cabled to
that city and the departure from Eng
land of the greatest steamship in the
world was heralded far and wide. For
several days there could be no
news of her. She might speak other
ships, bound for foreign ports, or
ships headed as she was yet which
must bow to her superior speed and
?,,, ? -K SI- * ?
^--.vaac.
The Titanic as She Was When She
Started on Her Tragic Voyage.
follow her wake up New York Harbor,
but no word could come from them
sooner than from the Titanic herself.
New York settled down to await the
first report from the big ship, and it
came on Sunday, April '14, when, at
2:15 A. M., the Titanic was reported
1,284 miles east of Sandy Hook and
due in New York at 4 o'clock Tues
day afternoon.
The giant liner was no four-day boat.
In speed she could not compete with the
Lusitanla or ! Mauretania, though to
no others need she yield, but New York
was content to wait for the coming of
the greatest ship afloat.
The report from the Titanic would
come on Sunday in time for publication
in the newspapers of Monday morning,
and should show her 500 miles or more
nearer New York. That was the mes
sage which was awaited. Instead, late
on Sunday night, this is the message
which came:
CAPE RACE, Newfoundland, Sun
day night, April 14.?At 10:25 o'clock
to-night the White Star Line steam
ship Titanic called " C. Q. D." to the
Marconi wireless station here and re
ported having struck aa Iceberg. The
steamship said that immediate assist
ance was required.
Half an hour afterward another mes
sage came reporting that they were
sinking by the head and that women
were being put off in the lifeboats.
The weather was calm and clear, the
Tltanlc'8 wireless operator reported
and gave the position of the vessel as
41.46 north latitude and 50.14 west lon
gitude.
The Marconi station at Cape Race
notified the Allan liner Virginian, the
NfAW?v?0<M>,
Capt. A. H. Rostron, Commander of
the Carpathia, Which Rescued
the Survivors.
Captain of which immediately advised
that he was proceeding for the scene
of the disaster.
The Virginian at midnight was about
170 miles distant ffipm the Titanic and
expected to reach that vessel about 10
A. M. Monday.
2 A. M., Monday.?The Olympic at an
early hour this (Monday) morning was
in latitude 40.32 north and longitude
61.18 west. She was in direct communi
cation with the Titanic and is now
making all haste toward her.
The steamship Baltic also reported
herself as about 200 miles east of the
Titanic and was making all possible
speed toward her.
The last signals from the Titanic were
heard by the Virginian at 12:27 A. M.
"The wireless operator on the Virginian
says these signals were blurred and
ended abruptly.
This was the first word of the disas
ter received in, America. It was not
until many days later that authentic
news of the striking and sinking of the
Titanic was received, and it became
known how the accident had occurred.
Many of the facts were gathered
from the testimony of J. Bruce Ismay,
President of the International Mercan
tile Marine; Second Officer Charles
Herbert Lightoller of the Titanic, and
Harold Bride, the Marconi operator
aboard the Titanic, which was given
The Carpathia, Rescuer
before the Senate Investigating Com
mittee.
Their statements established the fact
that it was a clear, cold night when the
Titanic plunged into the iceberg. The
big vessel had been four days on her
way. Such passengers as had been un
acquainted when the steamship left
port, had established the cordial rela
tions which usually exist among fellow
passengers on an ocean voyage. Din
ner .was over and there were groups of
carefully gowned women and men in
evening clothes in the saloons. The
smoking rooms were filled. There were
games of bridge and other hazards at
cards in progress.
Outside the temperature had been
falling rapidly as the Titanic drew
nearer and nearer to the ice floes from
the midst of which rose the group of
icebergs on one of which the great ship
was to strike. Tests of the water had
been taken every two hours throughout
the day and evening, but these as yet
had failed to show a dangerous prox
imity to the ice field. The officers
were not alarmed, and in the mind of
no passenger, probably, was there a
thought of danger. The Titanic, they
believed, was unslnkable.
The big ship was plowing ahead at
good speed, and Second Officer Lightol
ler, who had taken the bridge at 6
o'clock, was still on duty. It was early
evening. In the crow's nest were Sea
men Flint and Leigh, keeping a sharp
watch ahead, for though the iceberg
fleet was not dreaded, it was known
to be near at hand. There were no
other lookouts except the men on the
bridge.
At 8:55 o'clock Capt. E. J. Smith j
mounted the bridge and consulted with
his second officer. The ship was mak
ing twenty-one or twenty-one and a
half knots. The weather was fine and
clear. A myriad stars dotted the heav
ens.
Capt. Smith spoke with Llghtoller of
the ice fields into which they were run
ning and* of the great Icebergs there.
Wireless warnings of the existence of
these fields and bergs and of their loca
tion had been received by the Titanic
from her sister liners, the Olympic and
Baltic, from the Hamburg-American
11
of the Survivors.
liner Amerika, and from other liners.
Capt. Smith was serious but not
alarmed. He had been amply warned,
and if other ships could have traversed
the field in safety, surely the giant Ti
tanic could make the passage.
He ordered Second Officer Llghtoller
to keep the Titanic on her course, but
to notify him if there arose the slight
est doubt as to conditions. Then he
left the bridge at 9:25 o'clock.
Thirty-five minutes later Chief Offi
cer Murdock relieved Lilghtoller on the
bridge. The weather held fine and
clear, though cold. The temperature
was 31 degrees, but was not considered
abnormal for the region in which the
Titanic was. The men discussed the
ice fields and bergs which the ship was
approaching, and decided that they
probably would encounter them in
about an hour. Their estimate was not
far wrong in view of the uncertainty
as to the exact location of the fields
which were constantly moving with the
currents, for it was at 11:30 that the
Titanic scraped over a submerged shelf
of the berg, tearing away the steel
plates of her bilge.
Two facts stand out prominently in
the sinking of the Titanic. One Is that
had the look-outs in the crow's nest
been equipped with binoculars the dis
aster might have been averted. The
iceberg which sent the great liner to
the bottom was sighted when there
was yet time to turn the steamship
sufficiently from her course so that
the impact of collision was felt by the
liner's starboard bow some twenty feet
from the stem. The warning given a
few seconds before probably would
have allowed time for the Tltanlo to
have been turned aside beyond the
range of the berg.
The other fact is that many persons,
most of them men. lost their lives need
lessly. Not one of the lifeboats which
pulled away from the sinking Tttanlo
apparently went with a full cargo.
Some of them carried less than half
the number which might have found
room in them. That this was so was
the result of the demre of most of the
men aboard to remain there till every
woman had been removed.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1931-03-29/ed-1/seq-79/#date1=1756&sort=relevance&rows=20&words=</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Titanic Memorial to Be Unveiled in May]
%&&&
•——JHEMk^H
[ BY WILLIAM A. MILLEN.
_ -—EAR the City Mall in Belfast, Ireland,
. 7\ 7 stands an impressive monument
jj \/ commemorating the liner Titanic,
Y V built in that North Country capital,
*. and Washington will soon have as
Its latest memorial a monument that will con
jure up tragedy and peril and heroism on the
the high seas, the crunching of ice on steel,
•nd disaster nearly a score of years ago.
The Titanic Memorial is located at the foot
of New Hampshire avenue on the banks of the
Potomac River and has been in place for some
months. It will be unveiled in May as a lasting
reminder of that great maritime disaster. The
Belfast Memorial is hard by the River Lagan
and the famous cluster of shipyards, known as
“The Island,” from whose ways have slid down
▼easels to the four comers of the earth, among
them the Titanic.
Original plans for the unveiling in Washing
ton directed that it take place on the anniver
sary of the sinking of that ill-fated vessel,
majestic queen of the seas that went down in
a collision with one of the Ice King's minions
straying southward from the polar North. In
view of the unusual Weather conditions that
have prevailed for the past several months, the
sponsors of the unveiling have now decided
that the ceremony should be deferred until
May, when the weather is likely to be more
settled.
TJTGH hopes and despair; skill of craftsman
ship and maritime inefficiency; the latest
•f man's leviathans meeting disaster at the
hands of one of the world's oldest forces and
radio, playing a master part in the grim tragedy
that evoked primitive instincts of the fight for
life, are strangely mingled in this story that
will be perpetuated along the Rock Creek and
Potomac Parkway for the future generations of
Washingtonians.
There were sturdy men from the Counties
Antrim and Down, in Northern Ireland, in that
great giant of a ship, the Titanic, for had not
Belfast watched it grow with pride from just a
bit of a rib of steel to a magnificent hulk?
Belfast, more than any other city on the face
of the earth, stood aghast at the tragedy of
her sinking and felt more keenly her loss.
Belfast had fashioned this miracle of machinery,
had given of her best in her building, and then
ha/< sent her own as deckhand and fireman
over her gangplank, to sail away out of Belfast
Lough to Southampton on this Titanic, named
for the elder brother of Saturn, who made war
against him and was ultimately vanquished by
Jupiter.
The Titanic of the twentieth century met her
Jupiter as she was bound for New York some
where southeastward of Cape Race, Newfound
land, and some 1,600 miles from New York
City, in a colossal iceberg beneath the North
Atlantic stars. A compilation of figures made
soon after the tragedy says that the percentage
of women saved was 74, of children, 52, and
of men. 20. There were 817 passengers lost out
of 1,316. and 696 members of the crew went
down to a watery grave out of the total roster
of 908. Washington’s monument will do honor
to these brave men who stepped aside that
women and children might be saved.
Built at the famous shipyards of Harland &
Wolff for the White Star Line, the Titanic
steamed out of Belfast April 2 on her maiden
voyage. By April 10 she was out of South
ampton, England, and had made a call for
THF. SUNDAY • STAR, WASHINGTON. TV C, MARCH 29. 1931.
Appropriate Ceremonies to Honor the Heroes * «
j
of 111-Fated Ocean Finer—Statue at New
Hampshire Avenue and Potomac River.
]
~ !
One of the few pictures of the liner Titanic.
continental passengers at Cherbourg, on the
western coast of Prance, before heading toward
the setting sun. Queenstown, now known as
Cobh, in the south of Ireland, was her last port
of call, and she sailed blithely out into the
Atlantic breakers and on to disaster and the
fame that goes with great tragedy.
Capt. Smith, her skipper, was an officer of
some 40 years’ experience. On that happy day
in 1912, with the Pastnet and the hills of
Kerry drooping into the distance astern, as
lord of the Titanic he had achieved the zenith
of maritime ambition, for was not his craft the
mistress of the seas and Britain’s proudest
leviathan? Capt. Smith is said to have had but
one disaster in his long career on the waves
before the Titanic crashed.
RAILING supremely westward to the New
World, with glistening wood and steel, the
Titanic was a thing of beauty upon the sea.
Her passengers cavorted in the swimming tanks,
promenaded the decks, read In the spacious
lounges or listened to the latest music. Many
influential and powerful women and men in
the world of business, art, military and naval
circles and other lines of endeavor were aboard.
Out of the unseen came the first hint of grim
disaster, but little heed was paid. On the after
noon of April 14, 1912, the Titanic learned from
S. 8. America that that vessel had passed two
huge icebergs in latitude 41:27 north and
longitude 60:3 west. Similar warnings came
from the S. S. Baltic, on which Capt. Smith
had once served, and from the S. S. Californian,
but they were passed by.
That same evening the Titanic was steaming
westward at some 21 knots, with the weather
clear and bright starlight, when the lookout
shouted down to the bridge that there was ice
ahead. Contrary to popular belief, there was no
sudden lurch of the vessel as ice and steel met
in deadly collision, for authentic accounts of
the time say that many of the passengers and
crew did not know of the fatal impact.
As soon as the ice bank loomed up ahead in
the starlight night the engines were ordered
stopped and were then reversed, in an effort
to pull away from the wall of ice, and the
helmsman put her hard to starboard. Bulkhead
doors were closed from the bridge, according
to account, but all to no purpose, as the hidden
ice ledge had sheared eut part of the vessel’s
starboard side. The collision occurred about
11:40 pm. April 14 around latitude 41:46
north and longitude 50:14 west, just a com
paratively short distance from where icebergs
had been reported to her in the afternoon.
Boats were manned and lowered and cleared
from the vessel, but they were pitifully lacking
in equipment, and if the stories of the day
reflect the truth, there was an utter absence of
orderly safety measures, no general alarm and
insufficient lifeboats to care for all hands.
The vessel sank about 2:20 a.m. Monday,
April 15. 1912, and in that great tragedy the
history books have it that 1,517 lives were
lost. The horror of this major disaster oC
modern times swept the world, but the black
cloud of despair had its silver lining of stirring
heroism.
The Cunarder Carpathia. summoned by radio
by the disabled Titanic, added luster to the
name of Capt. Rostron, whose methodical com
mands for assisting in relief work are the
marvel of those that love efficiency in times
of peril.
“We are coming to your relief,” was the com
forting message that went out from the Car
pathian wireless shack into the night and
above the blue waves that carried the white
monsters of the deep—but it is doubtful if it
reached the wide audience it was intended for.
There were more than 2,000 persons aboard
the Titanic on the maiden voyage, and of that
number 1,517 perished. The tragedy would have
been even greater had it not been for the
efficacy of radio, which was to prove its mettle
for the first time in a major maritime disaster.
The Carpathia arrived about 8 am. and began
rescuing the occupants of the lifeboats.
QUT of that maelstrom of human misery have
come thrilling tales of heroism—Phillips
and Bride, the radio operators who refused to
leave their posts in the wireless “shack” of the
Titanic until almost the last minute, because
their skipper had not given the word to go,
even though the frigid waters were rising
momentarily. Phillips had time to give a cup
of water to a fainting woman in the hustle and
bustle of death. The musicians, too, played
their instruments and endeavored to instill
hope and courage into the hearts of the women
and children. Over the seas of memory eomes
the recollection of that hymn that was wafted
over the waters above the confusion and
tumult, “Nearer, My God, to Thee,” as the
Titanic was in her last throes.
Such as these will Washington’s monument
commemorate, though they sleep beneath the
waters of the North Atlantic. They will live
in the National Capital in a monument beside
a beautiful parkway on the banks of the
Potomac.
The magnitude of this tragedy at the front
door of the North American Continent had its
reverberations in the halls of Congress, which
inquired into the affair. Senator William
Alden Smith of Michigan made a speech on
May 28, 1912, and informed his colleagues of
the results of the investigation—a recounting
of inefficiency and culpability—of a lookout
that said he was without proper binoculars for
his work; of one of the icebergs, nearly 200
feet above the level of the sea, with seven
eighths of its bulk hidden beneath the waves;
of the sudden drop in temperature before the
Titanic struck; of the general air of indifference
on the part of the authorities aboard the
doomed craft, and of the lack of adequate
equipment to cope with such an emergency.
Maritime officials, after an examination of the
plans of the vessel, said that the double bottom
did not extend up the sides of the vessel in
order to assist in keeping her afloat after her
outer skin had been punctured and that her</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-ellis-island</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>/</id>
        <rel></rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/</id>
        <rel></rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-martians</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>/</id>
        <rel></rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>/</id>
        <rel></rel>
        <text></text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
